Leah: Hi, my name is Leah
Rhiannon: and I'm Rhiannon.
Leah: Welcome to our course
and understanding children and
young people's mental health.
Rhiannon: We will be with you
throughout your journey to provide
some useful information and clarify
further some of the elements you'll
discover yourself along the way.
Leah: We also interview professionals
from the industry as we go and talk
to some of the people who live with
mental health conditions day-to-day.
Rhiannon: All the way, strengthening
your knowledge and helping you to
become more familiar with children
and young people's mental health and
pass this level two certification.
Leah: So let's begin.
Shall we?
Rhiannon: This video is all
about the concept of mental
health and what it means.
Leah: We will look at how the terms used,
allow us to focus on different aspects of
mental health and look at the relationship
between mental health and wellbeing.
Rhiannon: Good mental health should
be looked at as a way of allowing
people to realise their full potential.
And it helps them to cope with
the stresses of life, be it in
their work, social interactions,
family life, or making meaningful
contributions to communities.
Leah: When people talk about mental
health problems, they're often talking
generally about mental ill health,
and this covers a very wide spectrum
from the everyday worries and grief
to the most bleak, suicidal thoughts
or total loss of touch with reality,
Rhiannon: Everyone responds differently
to stresses and strains of life, and
may often feel anxious or depressed.
But when those feelings become so
serious that they find it difficult to
function, then it becomes a real problem.
Leah: Resilience can give a person
their capacity to recover quickly from
difficulties and early identification,
coordinated support, and the
promotion of good mental health among
children and young people can help
improve their chances of recovering
and preventing mental ill health.
Rhiannon: Self-esteem is really
important as it influences
people's choices and decisions
and serves as a motivational tool.
It can give people the strength
to better take care of themselves
and explore their full potential.
Leah: Let's now look at the
relationship between mental health and
wellbeing as they are closely linked.
The environment a child grows
up in can have a real impact
on their overall wellbeing.
Rhiannon: Also, the security and positive
stimulation, a young child gets from a
parent or carer has a major impact on
their social and emotional wellbeing.
Providing a good foundation
for more healthy behaviors.
Leah: However, if not handled correctly,
family health problems and, or breakup
of the family can in contrast negatively
affect a child's mental wellbeing.
Rhiannon: It's important to promote good
mental health and wellbeing to build
the resilience of children and young
people, and ultimately for people's health
and wellbeing throughout their life.
Leah: Good relationships are important
in mental health and wellbeing.
They can help to build a sense of
belonging and self-worth and give
opportunities to share positive
experiences, provide emotional
support and work to support others.
Rhiannon: So let's explore a little
more into the understanding of children
and young people's mental health.